Hey guys, Shandid welcome back and today
in distributed microservices we are
going to cover logging. Okay, so it's a
very underrated topic but lot of good
questions can be asked in an interview.
So let's start without wasting any time.
What is logging?
It means recording important application
events like request, response, error,
warning or any information. Okay. So
that we developers can monitor and debug
what the application is actually doing
at runtime.
So for example,
you own the user component. Okay. And
you have one endpoint / post
which task is to create a user. So as
part of logging you can write any
information into the logs. So let's say
I am writing one event that user created
okay something and some additional
information. Now let's say in future if
a user comes that he or she is facing a
problem then you can check the
particular log and see okay I see this
printed into the logs mean till here my
code is working fine. So you see that a
log can help you in your debugging and
it is not like you have to only log
request or error or something very very
critical even some information which can
help you in the debugging that also we
can log or we can record.
Okay. So before we go with distributed
logging
where we have like multiple
microservices and all we first need to
understand how logging works in a single
application
and once that done
achieving this in a distributed logging
is very very easy. Okay. So see this
flow very important flow and here if you
see that the first is your spring boot
application. We have an application and
with this our application
the first the second thing you can have
is like SLF4J
uh you can say that interface. So this
is an interface which has only provided
APIs no implementation at all as SLF 4J
fullform is simple logging facade for
Java. So see even the full form has the
thing called facade. If you remember
from the low-level design facade design
pattern only expose APIs no
implementation.
So it's an interface actually.
So this is a logging interface or you
can say that uh a library which only
provide APIs for the logging but its
implementation. So there are different
libraries. So its implementation
generally we have log back which is the
default which is spring boot provide a
default. Okay. And we have another uh
framework is log 4j2. So this is also an
implementation of slf 4j. Okay. Log 4j2
full form is logging for java version 2
and the logback is the one uh which
spring boot provides you. Okay. So its
library automatically comes when you
export a spring boot application from a
spring initializer. So this library
automatically comes and also this this
interface already comes and this
implementation. So that's why I
mentioned default.
So now you got the implementation also
for the interface.
Now this implementation make use of
appender. So there is a concept called
appender. What does appender do? You can
say that it's a component whose task is
to decide the destination. Destination
of what? Destination of log.
So whatever I'm trying to log where it
will go whether it will goes to console,
whether it will goes to some file,
whether it will goes to DB, whether it
will goes to cloud or Kafka, whatever.
So where whatever you are trying to log
its destination is decided by appender.
Okay. So our implementation library make
use of appender
to generate an output. So output is like
if your appender is file appender then
your output would be some whatever the
file name you will give dot log a log
file will be generated. If you choose
console then all the logs would get
printed into your console a standard
output. Okay. So once the output is
generated then we have log aggregation
tools like data dog elastic search and
kibbana the prompt tail. So the these
tools read from the output. Okay. So
till our application you can say that
control is like where the output will go
and after that log aggregation tool task
is to read from that
file or console or place where the
output is kept.
Okay. So this is the flow.
So let's see what it takes to implement
the log functionality.
So here very very simple
I have one rest controller. So till now
whatever we have done take a very simple
spring boot application. So till all you
have a uh dependency is your web the
very basic one. Okay. And I have just
simple written a rest controller. And
here if you see
this is the first thing logger factory
dot get logger and given the class name
dot class. Okay. So with this I am
getting a logger object
and using this logger object
within a particular method I am just
logging a event log.info
f the payment successfully. Okay so I am
logging something
okay now if I run hit this endpoint
slash payments if I hit this / payments.
Okay. So it the output you see is that
successfully fetch all payments. So this
is the return type successfully fetch
all payments. But I'm also logging
log.info fetch the payment successfully.
So if you see the console. So this is my
console.
You see this f the payment successfully.
So logging worked.
So don't go inside this for now like hey
how it worked actually. But all I wanted
to show you that
you don't need any additional
dependency.
Okay. All you have to just is like
whatever the applications which you have
taken out from initializer with the
starting this web itself. So here if you
see that this okay this is the initial
spring boot starter web that's all.
Okay, with that itself you will get the
dependency of SLF 4J
because logger factory is present into
SLF 4j and you are hitting get logger
which is also present into SLF 4j and
its implementation is within this and
this is the default. This library also
comes by default log log back.
Okay. And also what is the default
appender? It's console appender is the
default. So they have one appender also
and default is console one itself. So
that's why whenever I do log info
ultimately where it goes to the console.
Okay, things will get little clear but
for now moto is that what it takes to
implement the log functionality. So if
you see that very simple all libraries
are already present you have to just get
an object and start logging the events.
Okay, but how it's working? What exactly
happened behind the scene? That is now
things will become interesting.
So first thing is dependency.
So when we add below dependency. So here
if you see that spring boot starter web
internally also bring spring boot
starter. Okay. So internally it further
add this dependency also. SLF 4G API jar
log back classic and logback core jar.
So these two is nothing but you can say
that part of an implementation library
and SLF 4J is the API
logger API. Okay. So these dependency
will automatically get added when you
add a spring boot starter dependency in
your application.
So one question might come to your mind.
Hey Shri, so by default Spring Boot
brings the logback library. Okay we got
it. Yes, it is bringing logback library.
But what if I want to use log 4j2
then I have to add dependency of log 4j2
like like so this is the dependency you
have to add a new dependency that org
springframework.boot boot spring boot
starter log 4j2. So this dependency we
have to add.
Now in the class path we have two
implementation of library of slf 4j. One
is which we have manually added log 4j2
and one which automatically
added by the spring framework in the
starter when it it comes with the
starter itself.
So which implementation library will be
used by the framework?
Because we have now two implementation
one we have added and one is added by
default.
So what this is a framework code. So if
you go inside log logger factory what it
does is internally if you see it will it
uh so it has a provide a list. So it
will get two and it simply do get zero.
So sometime you might see you get log 4
J2 sometime you get log back. So
definitely in production this is not a
reliable thing to do.
So here I'm just starting an application
with this. I have manually added it and
I know that by default spring framework
will also bring log back library also.
So if I started the application here if
you see it is also showing the warning
class path contains multiple SLF 4G
providers
but since it is doing get zero your
application will start normally but
whether it is using log back or log 4j 2
you don't it's doing get zero it can be
anything
so for production this is not reliable
instead we should specy specifically
exclude the default library. If you are
planning to manually adding the library
so let's say I wanted to use log 4j2 so
from this starter I have to exclude
the starter logging so this starter
logging actually brings this log back
classic log back core that that
implementation libraries I don't want so
these two implementation library comes
from starter logging okay so that's why
I have ex excluded it Okay. So from this
library exclude this logging sub library
you can say.
So got it. Uh
till now it is clear right?
Now let's go to the second part. So
dependency part is clear. Now let's
focus more on get logger object. So here
we are finding out a logger object.
Right? So here if you see what we are
doing is logger factory dot get logger
payment controller dotclass and it is
giving us a logger object.
So this logger is nothing you can say
that it's an implementation of slf for
4j generally we should be getting it. So
how this is working internally. So see
this is the you can say that UML diagram
internally of the logger framework.
So with this everything should be clear
like how it is working. So let's say
that this is first
logger interface
or do SLF4J okay this is an API.
Okay so that's why it's an interface. So
this class logger is an interface.
Okay. And that's what I am getting here
interface.
Now this interface is implemented by
multiple
libraries which are generally an
implementation of this SLF 4j. So I have
one logger class here present into the
logback also. I have the logger class
which is present into log 4j also.
Okay. So this logger has like logger
name, logger 11, logger level, parent
child information which we will see.
Okay. But for now understand that in SLF
4J has one class logger which is you can
say that it's an interface and this has
multiple implementation.
One implementation is provided by
logback classic. Another implementation
is provided by log 4j. So different
libraries different implementation of
this. Okay. So ultimately when we get an
object logger factory dot get logger we
get this logger
interface one. Okay. So ultimately this
interface holds an either
reference to either logback classic
logger or log 4j core logger.
Okay. So that is first thing. Now here
if you see when you do logger factory
dot get logger method when you invoke
this one what is happening? So control
is coming here logger factory. So logger
factory is part of API SLF 4j library.
So what it do is
it does two thing. First it find out
what's the implementation whether log
back is the implementation or log 4j is
the implementation which I have to use
and how it will determine from the
library in the class path which library
is present. Okay. So we have already
seen that
like whatever in the pom you have added
a dependency. If you have added log 4j
dependency you have to exclude this one.
Okay. Uh if you not then by default log
back will come. Okay. But anyhow only
one should be present. If you have two
then also it will do get zero. In the
class path it will have only one
provider. Okay. So it knows that from
the class path
which one is the implementation I have
to use whether log back or log 4j. Okay
then it calls I logger factory. So I
logger factory is also part of sl 4j. So
it has a method let's say get logger and
the name. So this name is nothing but a
logger name. So if you see that logger
each logger has a name.
Okay. So now this I logger factory. So
here if you see that it's an interface.
So see SLForge is nothing but an
interface. No implementation. So this is
also an interface. So it is implemented
by
classes which are present into either
logback or log 4j. So in logback let's
say one class is logger context which
implement this logger factory. And this
method get logger method is also provide
an implementation.
So here if you notice these classes they
maintain a cache
string, logger. So what it does? So when
you do logger factory dot get logger and
provide the name. So this is the name of
the logger actually.
So it will not create new object every
time. Okay. So what it will do is it
will first we are calling logger factory
get logger method. Okay. It will knows
that which library it has to use whether
log back or log 4j. Then it will pass
the request to logger factory. From
logger factory ultimately it goes to one
of the
get logger of either log back or log
forj. Now let's say that currently we
are using the default one. It will goes
to the logback one. Okay. Now here if
you see it is maintaining the map in the
get logger it first check this cache or
you can say that this map. So this
string is nothing but a name. Okay the
name which is this coming.
So if for this name logger is already
present so it will just reuse that
object.
It will not create new object every
time. So you can say that so for
one name one logger
is one logger object is present.
Similarly log 4j has also doing the same
thing but in a different way. So it is
also maintaining a map and it has its
own uh objects logger context and all
but the concept is same. They both are
doing caching. Okay. So for one name one
logger object should be present.
So when you do get logger what it will
do is it will check this map if the for
this name for this name if there is no
object present it will create one
object. So that's why I put a it has a
so it will create one object. So if
you're using a logback so it will create
one object of this and put into the map
and then ultimately return an object.
So this is clear
okay go through it again it will get
clear but yes this is the UML diagram
you can say that of a log framework.
So what logger factory does?
So this logger factory so logger factory
finds which SLF 4j implementation to
use. Okay. And it is done based on I've
already told you uh library which is
presented to the class path and invokes
the logger context of the specific
implementation whether it will call the
logger context. You can say that if it
is using log back if it is using log for
it will invoke this abstract logger
adapter
and this logger context generally here
I'm uh specifically saying from this uh
log back perspective but it's a logic is
same mostly for both log 4G also it does
caching based on the logger name and
logger name could be anything it can be
class name it can be package name or any
string. Okay. So if for a particular
name logger object is already present,
it reuse it.
Else create a new and put it into the
cache.
And then we have logger object. So these
are the logger objects.
So logger objects have few important
fields present within logger class. So
one is name,
level,
parent and child.
Okay, one parent, multiple childs. Now
let's see this because these are the
crux of the logging framework.
Name. So this is the name of the logger.
It can be anything I told you. It can be
package name, it can be class name or
any string.
So for a given logger name only one
logger object is created and reused. We
have already seen that. But in real
world application the common practice is
to create one logger per class. That's
why in production you always see that we
are doing payment controller dot class
the class name and then we put dot class
because it will use the name as a class
name. So when you are using like this
let's say my payment controller is my
class name. So when I use like this
payment controller dot class so the name
is that com.concepts dot payment
controller the full class path.
Okay. So this would be my name
of the logger and this is generally in
the production we say that one logger
per class otherwise
you can give any name. So it's like one
name one logger object.
So name is clear. Then we have level
very important.
So for each logger object
we configure a log level. So there are
multiple level. We have error, warning,
info which is the default, debug, trace.
So error has the highest priority you
can say and trace has the lowest
priority. Okay. So the priority goes
from top to bottom.
So for each logger object which we are
creating we can assign one log level to
it or you can say that not log level we
can assign a level to it. So level could
be one of this five. If you don't
provide this level by default it would
be info.
And now what happened is that each log
statement what we are doing is that log
debug. So this is one statement
log.debug log.info log error. So each
log statement implicitly also has a
level. Okay. So for now currently I am
putting log debug. So this log statement
has a level debug. So there are two part
a logger object. logger object has level
and the each log statement also has a
level. Okay.
Now what the purpose of this level? Now
you can see
the logger
prints a log statement
only if log statement level is same or
higher than the logger configured level.
So here if you see this diagram so this
is my logger object and the level I have
set is one let's say w a r and one this
is my level I have set so
each logger object we can set a level
now using this object I can log multiple
log statement logger object dot error so
this is one statement so I am this is
the error statement this is a warning
statement this This is a info log
statement. This is a debug statement.
This is a trace. Okay.
Now here I told you that logger prints
only a log statement
which has same or higher than the logger
configured level. So what is the level
one? What is the priority? This one. So
same or higher. So it will only
entertain this log statement which are
either warn or error. So only these two
would be entertained and this info debug
trace would be skipped in this case.
You got it? So only these two log
statement will be printed by the logger
as these log statement level is equal or
higher than the logger level. Logger
level is one. So equal or higher than so
error has higher priority than one and
one is equal. But this since these are
lower priority. So this would be skipped
because I have set my logger object
level. Okay. Enterain either one or
higher priority than this. And whenever
any statement comes I can either uh skip
it if its priority is less than what I
have set for my logger object.
So see this example uh simple program
the same thing. I am getting an object
of a logger.
Okay. And uh I haven't defined anything.
I haven't defined what's the level. I
haven't defined what's the level. So
what would be the default one? Info.
Okay. And I have log statement. Log
error. So using this object I am
creating multiple log statement. One is
error warn info debug trace.
Now when you run it, if you see the
default is uh info
for this my logger object for my logger
object. So it will only entertain info
and above. Okay. So error would be
entertained, warn would be entertained
info and but it will skip debug and
trace. So if you see this error, warning
info but no debug, no trace.
So we can change if you let's say if you
want to change the uh level from info to
let's say something else for this logger
we can change it through the
configuration. So in
application.properties we can change
logging dole
and now the name
name of the logger.
Okay. Logging dot level and then after
that the name of the logger whatever the
level you want
debug
one info capital letter like this you
can give. Now if I start the application
and hit this endpoint so I have a debug.
So I will only enterain equal or higher.
So error would be entertained warning
info debug. But trace is lower priority
than debug. So that would be skip
error warning info debug but trace is
skipped.
Okay. So level is clear.
Then we have if you see that the logger
object logger object has one parent and
the list of logger the child. What does
that mean? Very important topic. So here
this if you see this UML each logger has
parent and the list of child.
So what does that mean? So logger
framework
internally maintain the hierarchy of
logger objects.
So now let's say when you do this logger
factory dot get logger payment
controller.class. So this is nothing but
your class and its package is
com.concepts.p paymentcontroller. So
this becomes your name of the logger.
So what do you understand with this for
now till now that okay for this name one
logger object would be created. One
logger object would be created and put
into the map
that uh payment controller com
do.concept dot payment controller my
logger object. This would be created and
put into the cache. This is till now
what we understood.
But what I told you that logger
framework internally maintains the
hierarchy of logger objects. Okay. So
here if you see it create multiple
logger objects. This is
first logger object is the which name is
root. It is always created. You cannot
delete it. So it's a parent of all you
can say that always created by framework
itself. So this logger object is present
and its name is root.
Now
all the logger which you are going to
create further it it would be the child
of the root only. So now I have created
one object uh logger object for this
name com.concept.p paymentcontroller. So
first it will create it will create a
hierarchy. Okay. So it will create one
logger with the name com. So it will
create another logger object which is a
child of the root and its name is com.
Then it will create another logger
object which is a child of the com and
its name it will give com concepts.
com dot concepts.
Then it will create another logger
object which name is com.concept.p
paymentcontroller which is a child of
this com concept. Okay. So like that it
goes.
So maybe let's say some there are some
other folder. So not let's say org. So
there can have logger name equals to or
something. Okay. So like a tree it can
happen. So maybe inside this folder
com.concept concept you can have like
another logger which name equals to
let's say com doconcept do user
controller okay so you can have like
this so it creates a hierarchy so even
though you give let's say no uh name
like comconcept payment controller it
don't just create one object logger
object it will create multiple objects
in a hierarchy form
Okay. If you have like this,
if you have only one name, let's say uh
payment controller, this is the name,
then definitely it's just directly under
the root, let's say. But root is the
parent of all for sure.
Okay.
Otherwise, whatever the path you will
give, it will follow like this. So, if
you have given com.concepts.payment
payment controller. So it will create
one com then its child is com.
do.concept then it child is com.concept
dop payment controller. So like this
hierarchy would be made and this is if
you put a debugger point
okay and where you will put a debugger
point if you want to see this. So if you
can get to know from this itself
this UML.
Okay. So here if you see this logger
okay if you're using a log back if you
put at this logger class debugger you
will have all this information name
level parent child so that's what I did
I put a debugger point
and I got all this information so here
let's put that
so currently I have not added the lo for
Okay. Two. So I am using the default one
log back. So let me start an
application. Maybe debug point is
already present. Let me hit.
No debugger point is not there. So let's
put into logger
inside a log back.
Okay. So see it has name, it has level,
it has parent, child. So it has mostly
all this thing. So
let me put into log.info and from there
we will go. So let me hit it log.info.
Let's go inside this. I got into logger
on java. So logger on java is in which
one? Logback classic. So see this.
So currently com.concepts.p payment
controller its parent is com concepts.
So here let's see that
the same thing com.p payment.p payment
controller its parent is com concepts.
Now go to its parent. So name is com
concept. Its parent is logger com. So
its parent is this com. Now if you go
inside this com what its parent root so
hierarchy is maintained like this.
Okay. then com concept com root.
So root would always be there.
So you might be thinking what's the
advantage of maintaining the parent
child relationship, right? What's the
point that hey I have a parent and uh
like I also have a child information
that okay com has childcom do.concepts
like all this thing what's the point? So
one important point is log level
inheritance.
So we don't need to configure each and
every class. For example, I can set
level on package logger itself. And all
its child automatically inherited. So
here if you see I showed you one example
where we are setting the level for our
logger. Okay. Now let's say this is one
logger. It's this is the name.
Okay. Now let's say you have thousands
of classes.
Okay. Do you want to change?
So by default is info. Let's say you
want to change it to debug.
You have thousands of classes. Will you
change
for each class in the configuration that
logging dolevel.com
dotconcepts dot payment controller debug
logging.le.comconcept
do user controller debug like this no so
that's where log level inheritance comes
I can just login.le.com level.com. So I
can tell uh set the level till parent
which parent so let's say till this
parent I can set a level now all its
child classes will inherit this level
itself.
So like here I have done logging.
So till com I have said the level debug.
Now all its child
loggers will inherit this level. So now
I have uh hit this endpoint again. Okay.
Now here if you see what is the uh level
of the com is debug and this is like com
dot concepts dot payment controller. So
definitely it's a child of this com only
right. So debug is applied to this also
this logger also.
So debug is applied means this is
entertained, warning would be
entertained, info would be entertained,
debug would be entertained but trace
would be rejected because it has less
priority than debug.
So here if you see it's work
and also another advantage is that we
can override a specific child behavior.
So let's say that I have thousands of
classes. So that's why I have set at uh
my you can say that parent logger itself
that any child loggers which are under
this com use a level debug but for any
specific class or for any specific
logger you want to override it you can
do that
so that's why I'm doing
within this com there could be so many
loggers but for comconcepts do this
specific controller I can override to
that is also possible.
The third is that accepted logs are
propagated upward. This is very very
important.
Okay. So understand that if log is
rejected
stop do not propagate it. What does log
is rejected means? So we have already
seen that that u
here if you see this is one example of
log rejected here
let's say that what is the level of this
controller so logger logging dot level
and we have given the name of the logger
right com.concepts concepts dop payment
controller which is this logger we have
given debug this is the level now let's
say you are doing this let's say you
don't have this
you are trying to log trace trace log so
this trace priority is lesser than debug
okay the level of this logger so this
statement is rejected so this is known
as statement rejected log rejected
but this Other part if you see this
other logger logger
dot log dot error error log so this log
statement priority error is higher than
the level of this logger. So this is
accepted. So that's why it is known as
accepted log.
Now come back to again to that one.
If log is rejected stop do not propagate
it.
And that's what I have just uh told you
that what does log rejected means and
accepted log is propagated upward till
root and all appenders are executed very
important by default appenders by
default this propagation is true but we
can make it false we will see that
so
let's understand this propagation better
so I told you that this line Repeat it
again. Only accepted log is propagated
upward till root and all appenders are
executed. So appenders just to remind
it's a component that decide where the
log will go. It will go to the console
or file or DB or gafka or some cloud
etc. So this is just like decide where
the log will go and also we have seen
hierarchy like hierarchy is maintained
by the logging framework that the the
higher the parent of all is root and
after that it keep maintaining the
hierarchy.
Now see that
appender for each logger we can have an
appender.
Okay. So for some we don't have an
appender for some we can have an
appender.
Okay.
Now
here if you see what is the level of
this logger com do.concepts.p
paymentcontroller. So you understand
this hierarchy now right? So I have I
have this class I have created only one
logger object.
So you know that this payment controller
is like this package com dot concepts
dot payment controller but it don't only
create this object. It create a complete
hierarchy. It will create an object of
this com. Its child is then com concept
this one and then it will create com
concept payment controller which is a
child of com concept and ultimately
everyone is a child of this root one. So
root is at top.
So each logger we can have an appender.
So for now I am saying that maybe some
logger we cannot uh we don't have any
appender or some we have an appender
that let's say root is deciding it log
need to be printed to console
this uh logger com.concepts concepts
logger decide that log should be printed
to the file and for here I don't have
any appender I don't have any appender
now when you have this code now here if
you see what is the level of this logger
object payment controller right this one
the level is info
okay now you have a log statement log
info so definitely this would be
accepted because it has equal level of
the logger. So that would be accepted.
So what I told you that accepted log is
propagated upward till root and all
appenders are executed. So it once it is
accepted
okay it will
move upward. Okay first here it will
execute all appender at this level
first. So currently I don't have any
appender. So nothing will get printed.
So this log log.info info.
This is the info. Will it get printed
here in this logger? No. Because
appender is the one which decide the
destination of the log. So currently it
doesn't have any appender. So this
logging will not not be printed
currently anywhere. Then it will go
upward
to this one its parent. So it will check
does parent has any appender? It will
execute that. Okay. This parent says
that any log put it to file. So this
log.info
this statement goes to the file. This
appender got executed. Then it goes
upward. Then it will say is there any
execute appender? No. So it won't do
anything. It goes upward till root. It
will see any appender. Hey yes. What
this appender says that print this log
on the console. So what it will do is it
will print the log.info to the console
also. So here if you see
uh this log statement got added to this
file and also this got added to console
also.
So very important part is this line that
once a child logger is accepted
log event it will always propagate
upward and all parent appenders execute
regardless of the parent level. So
that's why I specifically mention here
that
payment controller has level info and
its parent com has level warning.
So now when this
log statement log.info info
okay and it is coming from this logger
payment controller so this got accepted
right this logger level is also info and
also I'm trying to log a statement is
info only so this is accepted so once
the log is accepted
it will just move upward goes upward and
run the appenders
now it will not check that okay the
parent logger what is the level
is only checked only at once. Once it is
approved, now it just goes upward and
execute the appender.
And if you notice one thing in all our
previous example, we have not written
any appenders
and still be able to see the logs on our
console. How? So this is we were doing
this, right? We just added rest
controller. In rest controller, we have
this log.
This will like this would be the name of
our logger. Okay. And you know that
object would be created in a hierarchy
form. Now when we are doing log.info
the by default we haven't provided any
level. So it by default
level of this logger would be info.
So now you are doing log.info.
So that has the same level. So this
statement would be approved.
Now this statement would be approved.
Now where it would be shown?
So this logger payment controller this
logger okay has any appender. We haven't
written any appender. So what it will
do? How in the console we are able to
see this how? So it goes upward. We
don't have any appender. It goes upward.
Com concept. Have we any appender? No.
So that will also not do. It will go up.
com has it created any appender we
haven't created right yeah even though
the name is comconcept
paymentscontroller
so internally it's created the object
with the name to maintain a hierarchy
but appender we haven't we haven't added
it so here also it won't do anything but
ultimately when it goes to the root root
has default console appender
so I told you that every log accepted
log goes up
and execute the appenders of the parent
till root.
So when it goes upward no appender no
appender no appender and ultimately in
the root we have one console appender
already present we don't have to write
it and that's why
it print into the console.
So that's why I told you that when we
don't specify the appender accepted log
propagate upward and a root logger which
framework provides we don't write it it
has a console appender present and it
print on the console.
Okay.
So in the next part there are so many
things we have to cover like how to
write this appender different type of
appenders
uh file console db so many types of
appender then we have log format
different format of log. So currently of
you see that format is this you have a
date then you have thread info then you
have uh this logger name and then
ultimately this. So we can even change
this format also. Log rotation, MDC,
correlation ID, a sing logging,
structured logging, PII very important.
We in the logs we never have to log the
PII data. We will come to that
distributed logging ultimately. So here
if you see there are so many things to
cover and we'll see you in the next part
because otherwise the part this part
will become too too huge and too long.
So my expectation here is
go through this video again okay and try
to implement it open the code see the
flow
okay and things will get clear but the
thing is like we have covered the flow
architecture UML
and level
and uh child and parent relationship so
if those are clear these These are you
can say that the foundation of the
logging.
Now this would become very easy like the
future task right we it might be seems
like okay we have still have so many
things to cover but here if you see if
we have clear with the flow okay where
is the appender what does appender mean
okay and where is it exactly fit into
the whole design then it's just like too
quickly we can do log format log
rotation this is simply just you can say
that features which is like now get
added into the existing flow existing
architecture which we have covered till
now.
Okay. So see you soon and if any doubt
let me know we can discuss into the
further section comment section. Okay
guys thank you. Bye.